Today's דף daf *daf* is דף ו *daf vav*, I believe, is
that correct? And we start with the משנה mishna *mishna* on ה
עמוד ב *hey amud bet*. So we're a bit behind, let's get
moving. And the משנה mishna *mishna* says as follows: הנושא שקלו לחברו
ושקלו על ידו *Ha-nosei shekalo le-chavero ve-shaklo al yado*. So we had
this phrase before על ידו *al yado*, does it mean for someone
or someone for you? Either way, you gave a שקל shekel *shekel*
to your friend and your friend should give it for your sake.
Give
the שקל shekel *shekel*, go ahead, you're going to the where you
know to the local square and to the village where they are
collecting שקלים shekalim, *shekalim*, give my שקל shekel *shekel* for me. ושקלו
על ידי עצמו *Ve-shaklo al yedei atzmo* and you forgot, presumably it
was an innocent mistake, and you put the שקל shekel, *shekel* in
the box for yourself. You had in mind that this will be
my שקל shekel. *shekel*, not your friend's שקל shekel, *shekel*. Now, this
gets to the issue which we addressed yesterday, which is once the
שקל shekel *shekel* is set aside, it is קודש *kodesh*, הקדש hekdesh
*hekdesh*. The גמרא gemara. *Gemara* had a whole question of how could
you take a שבועה *shvu'ah* on it, you don't take a שבועה
*shvu'ah* on הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*. So presumably when your friend, we'll call
him, when ראובן Reuven *Reuven* gave to שמעון *Shimon* the שקל shekel.
*shekel*, ראובן *Reuven* had already sanctified it and he gave it to
שמעון *Shimon*. And when שמעון *Shimon* gave it for his sake, שמעון
*Shimon* was taking a הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* coin and trying to use
it essentially for שמעון *Shimon* to get out of his obligation, his
financial obligation. Again, it wasn't voluntarily, it wasn't with knowledge, it wasn't
intentional, it wasn't malicious, right, but nevertheless, it was an honest mistake
and he tried to take this הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* coin that was
ראובן *Reuven*'s שקל shekel. *shekel* and use it for himself. So, here's
the הלכה halacha *halacha*, now you have the discussion of מעילה meila
*me'ila*. אם נתרמה התרומה im nitrema hateruma מעל *Im nitharma ha-trumah ma'al*.
Once the תרומה teruma *trumah* is taken, remember this was when the
temple, when the בית המקדש beit hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash* takes from the
moneys and takes an offering, as it were, a removal of funds
from the moneys and begins to use them, then that's considered then
the money has already been, before we learned it's like the money
has already been received by the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*.
And here the relevant issue is it's like it's been used. And
once something has been used, then you get to a מעילה meila
*me'ila* problem. So the act of מעילה meila *me'ila* was not done,
no benefit was accrued at the moment that the שקל shekel. *shekel*
was given, even given mis-correctly, but there's some sense of it being
used and therefore benefit accrued once the בית דין Beis Din *Beis
Din* takes the תרומה teruma *trumah* from the received שקלים shekalim. *shekalim*.
We'll see why in the גמרא gemara *Gemara*. Now, השוקל hashokel. שקלו
מן ההקדש ונתרמה התרומה וקרבה הבהמה *Ha-shokel shiklo min ha-hekdesh ve-nitharma ha-trumah
ve-karvah ha-behemah*. Now let's say you accidentally not from your friend's שקל
shekel *shekel*, your own money that you had lying around the house
that was הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* money, money that you had sanctified to
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*, money that was מעשר שני
Maaser Sheini. *ma'aser sheni* money, and you went ahead and you accidentally
used that to pay your שקל shekel *shekel* with that money. So,
will you do מעילה meila *me'ila*? Again, on your own הקדש hekdesh
*hekdesh* funds that you've misused. So here, interestingly, the end of the
משנה mishna *mishna* doesn't focus on the תרומה teruma *trumah* aspect of
it, when the funds were sort of, you know, transferred, but it
focuses on when the funds were actually used למעשה *le-ma'aseh* and practiced,
the קרבן korban *korban* was brought and offered. So, let's see that
again. השוקל שקלו מן ההקדש *Ha-shokel shiklo min ha-hekdesh*, you gave your
שקל shekel. *shekel* from הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* funds, ונתרמה התרומה *ve-nitharma ha-trumah*,
the תרומה teruma *trumah* was taken then of the שקלים Shkalim *shekalim*
given into the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*, וקרבה הבהמה *ve-karvah
ha-behemah*, and the money was not only funds removed from the general
collection box, but the funds were then applied and an animal was
bought and the animal was offered from those funds. Then מעל *ma'al*.
That's when מעילה meila *me'ila* takes effect. Now, that's if it's הקדש
hekdesh *hekdesh* funds, funds that were sanctified. What if it's ממעשר שני
מדמי שביעית Shevi'is, *mi-ma'aser sheni mi-dmei shvi'is*? Let's say you realize after
you paid your שקל shekel. *shekel* that you did it from מעשר
שני Maaser Sheini *ma'aser sheni* money or from שמיטה Shmita. *shmittah* money.
In that scenario, if you realize soon enough, there's a way to
get out of it, יאכל כנגדן *yokhal kenegdan*. You can eat corresponding
to them, meaning what we'll see in the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is
you can transfer the קדושה kedusha *kedushah*. You can say I know
I accidentally gave a שקל shekel *shekel* from מעשר שני Maaser Sheini.
*ma'aser sheni* money, wherever that מעשר שני Maaser Sheini *ma'aser sheni* money
is, that קדושה *kedushah* should be transferred
to this coin or to this food and then you are able
to eat the corresponding food. Of course, the point is that what's
not clear is that you should have the same option by הקדש
hekdesh *hekdesh*. If you realize before it's too late that you gave
a הקדש Hekdesh. *hekdesh* coin, why don't you say wherever the הקדש
hekdesh, *hekdesh* money is, I transfer the קדושה *kedushah* from that money
to this money?
How about an animal itself?
No, it was a, well, you mean after the animal's been bought?
Yes. No, yes. That is, okay, then it's too late, then the
funds have been used, but when you're transferring the מעשר שני Maaser
Sheini קדושה *ma'aser sheni kedushah* is before the animal's been bought. So
at that scenario, you didn't give an animal, right, you gave money.
Right, right. But let's say I מקדיש makdish *makdish* an animal.
Oh, no, then you can only redeem it if it gets a
מום mum *mum*. But in this case, it's all about money because
you give money as your שקל shekel.
*shekel*. Okay, so it's one level removed from the actual קרבן korban
*korban* itself.
Yes, correct. Until it actually becomes only something if it's קדושת הגוף
*kedushas haguf*, if it's a thing that has intrinsic קדושה *kedushah* and
is going to be used as a קרבן korban *korban*, it can
only be redeemed with a מום *mum*. But anything that's basically value,
you know, objects that are going to be transferred for then the
use of something else. that value can then be transferred in to
be redeemed and it can be redeemed. So why it only says
it by מעשר שני Maaser Sheini and not by the second case
of הקדש hekdesh is not clear. But the other thing that's not
clear is the question at what stage is the מעילה meila occur
when the funds have been just this תרומה teruma taken from the
funds or when the funds of an animal's already been brought? So
let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara Just one second. השוקל.
So the גמרא gemara. says אנן תנינן anan teninan we teach in
our משנה mishna אם קרבה הבהמה im karva habehema that if the
בהמה behema has been brought. דתני דבי רבי detani devei rebbi but
in the house of Rebbi they teach אם נתרמה התרומה im nitrema
hateruma if the תרומה teruma has been taken. Now this basically seems
to say as you can see once again there's all these questions
with the גירסא girsa but it seems to actually say remember I
actually told you also
that there's a whole question what is the משנה mishna that the
ירושלמי yerushalmi had. So the גירסא girsa as we have it some
reverse the גירסא girsa but the גירסא girsa as we have it
say our משנה mishna says the moment of מעילה meila is when
the בהמה behema is bought but Rebbi's משנה mishna or when the
בהמה behema is offered says it's when the תרומה teruma is taken.
That actually would be good because if that was the ירושלמי yerushalmi
גירסא girsa then the first part of the משנה mishna and the
second part of the משנה mishna would be consistent. Whether it's you
using your friend's שקל shekel whether it's you using your own הקדש
funds the moment of מעילה me'ila takes place when the בהמה behema
is bought. Then it just says brought I'm sorry you're right brought
brought. The only thing it's saying is there's another משנה mishna from
Rebbi's school that says interesting Rebbi's not the author of this משנה
mishna I thought Rebbi was the author anyway there's another משנה mishna
from Rebbi's school that says it's when the תרומה teruma is taken.
So anyway that makes it clear if you read it that way
that there are these two separate traditions. Is the מעילה me'ila? when
the animal is brought is the מעילה me'ila when the תרומה teruma
is taken? Our משנה mishna as we have it in front of
us which is not we don't know what the ירושלמי yerushalmi משנה
mishna was this was just the publisher put this משנה mishna in
that has as it were section from each of those traditions. The
first case
of your friend's שקל shekel, speaks about when the תרומה truma was
taken as the critical point and the case about your own הקדש
talks about when the בהמה behema was brought. And the ירושלמי yerushalmi
never tries to reconcile the first part of the משנה mishna and
the second part doesn't see the contradiction which again reinforces the idea
that the ירושלמי yerushalmi had it all consistent. The ירושלמי yerushalmi משנה
Mishna was all defined on when the בהמה behema was brought but
they recognize another tradition from the משניות mishnayot of Rebbi or something
that it was when the תרומה truma, was taken which is the
critical point for when מעילה me'ila takes place. So let's see what
the answer is. מתניתין
דבני מערבא.
matnitin devnei
maarava.
No I am aware but I am aware that there's a lot
of scholarship around what was the משנה Mishna that the ירושלמי yerushalmi
had. By the way we've never said it yet but it needs
to be said that the ירושלמי yerushalmi was not written in ירושלים.
yerushalayim.
ירושלמי yerushalmi is a complete misnomer. It's either called תלמודא דבני מערבא
talmuda devnei maarava of ארץ ישראל eretz yisrael or תלמודא של ארץ
ישראל. talmuda shel eretz yisrael. I mean we call it ירושלמי yerushalmi
but let's just be clear it's not written in ירושלים. yerushalayim.
It's somewhere in Israel. Yeah exactly.
Okay מאן תנא man tana
so the גמרא gemara says like this. So how do you deal
with this? Is it is the critical point when the קרבן korban
is brought or is the critical point when the תרומה truma is
taken? So the גמרא Gemara says מאן תנא man tana אם נתרמה
התרומה who is the author that says the critical point is when
the תרומה truma was taken? רבי שמעון היא rebbi shimon hi it's
Rebbi Shimon. דאמר רבי שמעון deamar rebbi shimon Rebbi Shimon would say
ידא דמקבל מעותא והכהנים זריזים הם. yada demakabel meota vehakohanim zerizim hem.
So the question would be we have the funds of the שקל
shekel when did we actually pay the people who sold the animals
for their animals? So there's a debate. So the חכמים chachamim say
we wait until we're מקריב makriv the animal and then we pay
them because we're afraid that we'll pay them first and then maybe
some problem will happen with the animal and so we'll have paid
them before and then we won't have used
it's not their fault but whatever הקדש is able to arrange things
for its own interests. So we'd rather wait to pay them till
the animal is actually brought. And Rebbi Shimon says no we pay
them immediately as we buy the animal and therefore and then we're
not afraid that something wrong will happen to the animals the כהנים
kohanim are careful.
I'm sorry if I sell you a perfectly good animal and then
in your under your carelessness it gets a מום I wouldn't get
paid? Is that how it works?
All right let's see we'll see when we get to it in
the גמרא. Gemara I don't want to get into that right now.
Right now the only question that's in front of us is not
what's the nature of that debate of Rebbi Shimon and the חכמים
chachamim but the practical question of when would the seller be paid.
So what the גמרא Gemara is assuming is the following is that
if you pay the seller right away then if you wait to
pay the seller till the animal is sold
and Michael's question is a good one what entitles you to wait
and so on we'll worry about that later but if you wait
till that point then the money isn't used until the animal is
bought and that's the author of our משנה Mishna. that says you
haven't done מעילה me'ila until the money was used meaning and when
is the money used when the animal's actually bought as a קרבן
korban, then you will pay the person who sold you the animal.
The בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash will pay that person who has provided
the animal the wholesaler the supplier. Whereas according to רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*, that the supplier is paid upon delivery and not
paid upon when the animals are actually brought as a קרבן *korban*,
then the money gets used earlier. Now I must say I still
don't fully understand it because the moment of נתרמה התרומה *nitrama hatruma*
is not necessarily when you're actually buying the animals, right? First you
remove the תרומה truma *truma* from all the place, from the big
box it's been collected in, and you don't buy, if you only
did that three times a year, we're going to learn in a
משנה Mishna *mishna*, you don't buy 100 animals at once. I mean,
the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*
had like four or five animals at one time. So I don't
exactly understand why the moment of נתרמה התרומה *nitrama hatruma* is assumed
to be the moment that you're paying the supplier. But that's what
the גמרא Gemara *gemara* here assumes, that everybody agrees the מעילה me'ila.
*meila* takes place when the moneys are used, and the question is,
are the moneys used right after the תרומה truma *truma* is taken,
or the moneys only used and given to the supplier once the
animal is brought? I also want to point out that it is
interesting. Yesterday we learned that from my sort of financial responsibility of
have I delivered the moneys to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis
Hamikdash* and have they left my control and gone into the control
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*, the key moment was
נתרמה התרומה *nitrama hatruma*. That was agreed upon. Certainly everybody would agree
once I put the money in the box, I've sort of given
my שקל shekel, *shekel*. But for the issue of מעילה me'ila *meila*,
it's not enough to give it, it actually has to be used
and that's what, and here the question is, when is it used?
When is it given over to the supplier? Now there was a
question, Charlie.
I just looked ahead, I think the next line addresses it.
Okay, fine. Alright, so let's keep look at the next line of
גמרא Gemara *gemara*.
Okay. וקשיא *Vekashya*. Now I got a problem. גנב ולסוף חברו *ganav
u'lesof chavero*, I went ahead and I stole Charlie's עולה olah. *olah*.
ושחטה סתם *ushchato stam*, and I brought it to the בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash* and they שחט *schechted* it or I שחט
*schechted* it without thinking it's Dov's קרבן *korban*. They just שחט *schechted*
it. So whose קרבן *korban* would it be? It would be Charlie's
קרבן *korban*. Okay. סתמא לשם בעלים הראשונים משתכחת *stama leshem baalim harishonim
mishtachacha*. So obviously it would work for Charlie. So the גמרא Gemara
*gemara* says I don't get it. You went ahead, you put your
money in the box, it was not say, there was no explicit
designation, "This is my funds," like you just put your money in
the box. When the money is used, it's at the end of
the day it was Charlie's money that was being used. So what
should be the whole issue of מעילה me'ila. *meila*? Just by the
way that the money is, doesn't matter what I that I thought,
"Oh, this is going to be my שקל shekel, *shekel*." In the
end, Charlie's שקל shekel. *shekel* found its way into that. Why is
there any misuse of the money? So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says,
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara. *gemara* says, אמר רב
יהודה תפשוט במסוים *amar Rav Yehuda tifshot bimesuyam*. We're talking about a
case where the money is
designated, well-defined, like you know, as again we had that case before
about remember funds that were given that were like fungible and something
that was given that was very concrete and identifiable. So somehow this
was a שקל shekel. *shekel*, I don't know, that Charlie had written
on it, "Charlie's שקל shekel *shekel*." Actually no, not that way, then
we'd know it's Charlie's. I had scribed on it "Dov's שקל shekel,
*shekel*" or something like that, you know, sort of scraped into it,
and then I gave it. So then when that שקל shekel. *shekel*
is being used or השקל *hashekel*, it's in by the fact that
it's well-defined, somehow it's implicitly being used for me. And therefore it's
being misused because it belongs to Charlie. Again, to כהנים *kohanim* pay
attention if people know and they say it. I mean you could
imagine a case that a coin looks weird, it's like you know
an Indian Head penny or something like that, you know, that there's
something distinctive about the coin. But it's distinctive that it makes it
defined that it's for me and not for Charlie who originally owned
it. Hard to imagine what exactly the case is. Now I want
to read the next line. Again, there's a whole question whether the
next line belongs here or belongs later. Let's read the next line.
The next line says like this. משל בית רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
שהיה מתכוין ודוחף לתוך הקופה *mishel Beis Rabban
Gamliel shehaya mitkaven vedochef letoch hakuppa*. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says
like this: The קופה kupa, *kuppa* is not the box. The box
that the money originally was put into was the שופר shofar, *shofar*.
Again, it was like this, you know, pyramid-shaped thing so you have
a small slot and then it collects the money and you can't
stick your hand in and get it. When they remove the money
from the שופר shofar, *shofar*, the act of תרומה *truma*, it was
removed into a basket. You know, you know what the act of
תרומה *truma* is comparable to? It's like when the people go around
now and they collect the money from the vending machines, right? I
think that's like a good way of thinking about it, right? You
let all the money collect and then every so often you pay
a visit and you empty it all out and you collect all
the money. That's called the תרומה *truma* that they did from the
שופרות shofars *shofrot*. So that תרומה *truma*, they would empty it into
these big baskets. Okay. So it
says what בית רבן גמליאל *Beis Rabban Gamliel* used to do is
they didn't put it in the שופר shofar *shofar* and wait for
the שופר shofar. *shofar* to go to the basket. They wanted their
money somehow to be used like right away or something and they
put it straight, when they waited, I don't know, till the time
of collection and they put it straight into the basket, not into
the שופר *shofar*. So what difference does that make? So it sounds
like what the גמרא Gemara *gemara* is saying is, and therefore, if
you did that, I took Charlie's coin and I was going to
give it for me, and when they were taking it out of
the שופר *shofar*, I put the coin in and said "Here, this
is my שקל shekel, *shekel*." So at that moment, that might be
what makes it מסוים mesuyam *mesuyam*. It's not anonymous, it's not like
I put it in the שופר *shofar* and walk away, two months
later they take it. take it out of the שופר. I put
it straight in the basket and I call it my own, so
then somehow when they later wind up using that שקל, shekel, they're
using it as my coin and not Charlie's coin and that's the
misuse of the coin. That seems to be the answer of the
גמרא Gemara although some say that this line doesn't belong here.
Same thing with the שופר, right?
Yeah, but I think the point is that then it becomes anonymous.
You walk in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash. anonymously, you put your
money in the שופר, you leave, a month... You could, but it
sounds like it wouldn't have the same effect. It wouldn't make it
מסוים mesuyam because of the time break and the people using the
money were not around, you know, a month later they come they
take who- how do they know what you said at that time?
But if you basically as they're collecting the money you put it
in their hand and say here, here's mine. I want you to
use that when you buy a קרבן somehow that makes it like
oh then they're using it for mine and I'm misusing Charlie's. It's
not automatically just because it's anonymous being used as Charlie's שקל.
shekel It's גניבה geneiva מעילה though, isn't there? What?
Yes, well that's the question though what is the גניבה geneiva at
this stage. If I just if there was no designation, then I
effectively Charlie gave me his half שקל, shekel I put it in
the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash. they wound up using it. The fact
that in my head I was thinking it was mine, what's exactly
the act of גניבה? geneiva? So that's sort of what the גמרא
Gemara is trying to get to. Okay, I'm not going to get
into all of מסכת מעילה. Masechet Me'ila. But it says the first
thing we have to decide is how was it anyway misused? It
was misused because I labeled it and that made it considered used
for me. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says דחש לומר שמא
לשיריים הנפקו. dechash lomar shema lishiyuraim hanofku. This is why people took
out the line before because this question in a way is already
answered. The גמרא says why when the money is used to buy
the קרבן or the תרומה is taken do I do מעילה? Let's
say I put it in the שופר and they did the תרומה,
but maybe when they did the תרומה they didn't totally empty out
the שופר. They just they just emptied out like you know a
certain amount of it. So maybe the point I put in was
left behind, was the שיריים. shiyuraim. And therefore even when the תרומה
was taken, even when the animal was bought, how do you know
that's the key moment? My coin might have been left behind. Of
course now if we say that I put it straight into their
hands, that's already our answer. Okay, which is why some say that
that line before actually didn't belong before. So let's take a look.
וכי יש מעילה בשיריים? vechi yesh me'ila beshiyuraim? Would you do מעילה
if the stuff was left behind? אלא כרבי מאיר. ella keRabbi Meir.
So one answer is it's going like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. דרבי
מאיר אמר מועלין בשיריים. deRabbi Meir omar mo’alin beshiyuraim. Yes, there would
be מעילה even if it wasn't used yet, even if it was
left behind, which is a strange idea. What's the מעילה exactly? Anyway,
we'll see רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir later. So it's- I don't- it's
hard to like- I'm not gonna try to try to explicate that
more now. But somehow רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says yes, when the
תרומה is taken, the act of taking the תרומה applies even to
the שיריים. shiyuraim. It's like the שיריים shiyuraim were used as well.
Yes, you do מעילה. A little hard to understand. או היא במסוים,
o hi bimesuyam, or another answer is like we said before, that
you designated the coin. ושל בית רבן גמליאל שהיה מתכוין ותורמו לשמו.
veshel Beis Rabban Gamliel shehaya mitkavein vetormo lishmo. And you would do
it for your name. Now again, again, you know, it's funny because
here when it says לשמו, lishmo, that should have been the line
we said earlier when the question was what makes it my שקל
shekel and not Charlie's. Here where the question is why isn't- how-
maybe it was left behind, we should have had the way it
said it before when it said דחפו לתוך הקופה. dochfo litoch hakupa.
By saying I put it into the קופה, kupa the קופה kupa
is what they're about to use. It's not the שיריים. shiyuraim. So
this same answer of using the רבן גמליאל scenario but the questions
and answers was reversed. What makes it my coin not Charlie's when
I I say this is my coin and I put it right
into their hands? What makes it not שיריים? shiyuraim? Because I put
it right into the קופה kuppa and I make sure it doesn't
get left behind. So that's the way the גמרא is explaining the
scenario. Now the גמרא still has another question. Good, we just figured
out how it's not automatically anyway just Charlie's שקל. shekel Fine, it
was my שקל. shekel, But what benefit did I get from it?
Now Michael said didn't I steal it? You can do מעילה by
stealing, not just by deriving benefit. But I never put it in
my pocket. In the end, I delivered it to the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, I just called it mine, so what type of- if
that's- that's not an act of stealing, what's the practical benefit that
I received, you know, that basically is going to be מעילה. So
the גמרא says מה נהנה? ma neheneh?
You didn't have to pay your own.
Well right. So what הנאה hana'ah do you get? אמר רבי אבין
בשם רבנן דתמן. amar Rabbi Avin beshem Rabbanan detaman. רבי אבין Rabbi
Avin says in the name of the Rabbis over there, presumably in
בבל, Bavel, מכיוון שבית דין ראוי למשכנו ולא משכנו כמו שנהנה. mikivan
sheBeis Din re’uya limeshkino velo mashkino kemo sheneheneh.
Because if you didn't pay, בית דין Beis Din would seize your
property. If you just get the שכר מצוה, s’char mitzvah, שכר מצוה
s’char mitzvah isn't the הנאה. hana'ah. Anyway, question how much שכר מצוה
s’char mitzvah you would get if you stole somebody else's שקל. shekel,
But the practical benefit is בית דין Beis Din isn't coming knocking
at your door and collecting. Now by the way, I was wondering
about that. If that's true, do you need the whole answer before?
Because even if in practice I didn't designate it and and they
went ahead and like as far as God is concerned it was
Charlie's שקל shekel. that was being used, but as far as בית
דין Beis Din is concerned it was my שקל shekel that was
being used, so even if it was not מסוים don't I still
get the practical benefit that they're not going to come collecting from
me? Right, you understand the question before was oh isn't it automatically
used for Charlie. Fine, but as far as as far as everybody
down here's concerned, I'm off the hook for paying my half שקל.
shekel So I don't know why that, and then they're going to
come to Charlie, so I don't know why that couldn't have answered
the earlier question.
That's a good question as to what's actually the act of the
גניבה? geneiva? Well, if I walk into your house and I say,
"this is my house now", yeah? Is it like that?
Well, yeah, but anybody,
you can't do that.
Right, well that's true, like a קרקע. karka. Right, so it's not
גניבה, geneiva, but in terms of the הנאה hana'ah that I get,
the הנאה hana'ah I get is that בית דין Beis Din stops
bothering me because they saw me pay the half שקל.
shekel Now he puts in a שקל shekel. and Charlie doesn't care
if somebody's taking...
Yeah, but he cares בית דין doesn't come and ask him a
second time. I understand.
But if you made a thousand dollar, if you made a thousand
dollar, what do you call it? Contribution or no,
what do you call before you actually make it or... Pledge, thank
you, and then you know you've given it, but the שול shul
thinks you haven't given it and they call the sheriff to come
take a thousand dollars out of your house, then you're going to
care, right? So it's not just about the מצוה, mitzvah, it's about
whether they're going to come knocking at your door.
ברוך השם. Baruch Hashem. How would they know who gave and didn't?
Like are they like...
That is a very good question. Who kept the rolls? Who kept
track?
I mean they have to go...
it sounded before that each village would collect and send its שקל.
shekel So presumably it would be handled at the local village level,
okay, and maybe the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash would coordinate with the
village and find out or whatever. But then also people who didn't
give would come to give individually. I have no idea. It would
have been a lot easier if it was on computer unless it
was like the health plan right now. So anyway, alright, let's... מעשר
שני. Maaser Sheini
Okay, so now מעשר שני Maaser Sheini, you could just transfer it
to the, to the food you have if you realized you gave
מעשר שני. Maaser Sheini, So דכתיב אך בכור אשר יבכר בבהמה לא
יקדיש איש אותו. dechsiv ach bechor asher yivakar ba-behema lo yakdish ish
oso. כל שהוא קודש, kol shehu kodesh,
so don't sanctify a בכור. bechor. Anything that's already sanctified אין קדושה
חלה עליו, ein kedusha chala alav, you can't put another sanctity on
it. So you can't go ahead and sanctify the מעשר שני money
for, you know, for מחצית השקל. machatzis hashekel. I don't know why
the משנה Mishna had to say that besides that you can't sanctify
it, you know, it's... if it can't be used for the מחצית...
machatzis... well because it's going to be used for a קרבן, the...
I mean the מעשר שני money has to be used to eat
in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. I mean if it's a שלמים shelamim it's one
thing, but it's an עולה. olah Anyway, כל שהוא קדוש אין קדושה
חלה עליו. kol shehu kadosh ein kedusha chala alav. Anything that's already
sanctified, another sanctity cannot take effect on it. So כיצד הוא עושה,
keitzad hu oseh, what do you do if you realize you gave
the מעשר שני money? מביא סלע של חולין ואומר, meivi sela shel
chulin ve'omer, you bring a coin of חולין chulin and you say...
it says סלע, sela, which actually a סלע sela is two שקלים,
Shkalim. anyway, מעות מעשר שני בכל מקום שהן הרי הן מחוללין על
סלע זו, maos maaser sheini bechol makom shehen harei hen mechulalin al
sela zo, wherever my מעשר שני money is, let the value be
transferred to this coin, ואותו סלע נתפס לשם מעשר שני, ve'oso sela
nitpas lesheim maaser sheini, that has, that's grabbed, that has the קדושה
of מעשר שני, והשאר נעשו שקלים vehashar na'asu shekalim and what's left
behind becomes your... gets to be your שקל shekel and then you
use this money. So you can do that for מעשר שני, you
can do that for שביעית, שמיטה. I don't know why the משנה
Mishna, assumes you can't use it for הקדש funds. Presumably הקדש funds
as well you can transfer הקדש funds, so I don't really know
the answer. Let's look now, ו עמוד א vov amud aleph at
the next משנה. Mishnah Okay, המכניס מעות ואומר הרי אלו לשקלי. Hamachnis
maos ve'omer harei elu leshkalai. So basically you're saving up penny by
penny over the year and you're putting it into a פושקא pushka
and you're saying that this is going to be for my שקל,
shekel technically my half שקל shekel, when it comes time. בית שמאי
אומרים מותרן נדבה. Beis Shammai omrim mosran nedava. And then when it
came time to pay the half שקל, shekel, you counted up your
pennies and you realized you had a whole שקל, shekel. alright, or
you had two-thirds of a שקל. shekel, What do you do with
the extra pennies? So בית שמאי Beis Shammai says look, when you
were putting them in the פושקא, pushka, you were saying this is
for my שקל. shekel.
Well, it's only because
you didn't know you had more. Okay, so this is a classic
debate of בית שמאי ובית הלל Beis Shammai u'Beis Hillel whether הקדש
בטעות hekdesh b'ta'us is הקדש or not. So that's essentially what you
were doing, right? When you say it's for my שקל shekel. you're
מקדיש it, and then it's הקדש בטעות hekdesh b'ta'us once you start
getting to more than the half שקל, shekel. you're just not aware.
So בית שמאי Beis Shammai says tough luck, it's still הקדש and
therefore it's נדבה. nedava. נדבה Nedava means it's money used by the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash to bring עולות olos when the, when the
המזבח, hamizbeach, when the altar is not active. Okay, so you use
it for בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, funds, not for the קרבנות ציבור
korbanos tzibur like the תמיד tamid and the מוסף, musaf, but you
still use it for the type of regular בית המקדש קרבנות. korbanos.
So a similar function as the שקל. shekel. ובית הלל אומרים, u'Beis
Hillel omrim, בית הלל Beis Hillel says מותרן חולין. mosran chulin. No,
it was a טעות, ta'us, so any leftover money is חולין. chulin.
Now I want to make it clear, it's not exactly the pennies
that you paid after the half שקל, shekel, right? We don't, I
can't identify which are the ones that you paid after the, you
know, once you already had half שקל, shekel, it's all mixed together.
But nevertheless, you take a half שקל's shekel worth and the assumption
is you only wanted to sanctify of all the money you were
putting in a half שקל's shekel, worth and anything that's more than
that you didn't want to sanctify. Of course it's a type of
a ברירה breira because, you know, six months later when you take
the half שקל shekel retroactively it identifies which were the ones you
sanctified and which were the ones you didn't, which is a whole
other issue. But fundamentally, anything over a half שקל shekel. you did
not want to sanctify. Now, שאלו מהן שקלים, she'elu me'hen shekalim,
let's say you didn't say, "These are for my שקל," shekel you
said, "From this money I'll draw on this money, I'll use some
from this money to bring my שקל," Shekel, but you're not saying
all of it. You're saying, "From it." So so therefore שוין shavin
בית שמאי Beit Shammai agree שהמותר she'hamotar חולין chullin anything left over
is חולין chullin cause you didn't say you were sanctifying all of
it, you just said you were sanctifying from it you would take
your
שקל. Shekel Okay. אלו לחטאתי eilu le'chatati now let's say you were
putting aside money and you said I'm going to use this for
my קרבן חטאת. korban chatat.
Everybody also agrees שאין she'ein שוין shavin they agree שהמותר she'hamotar נדבה.
nedava. There they do agree that it's not חולין. chullin. Why? We're
going to see in a minute because there's not no fixed price
to a חטאת. chatat. So if you're putting aside money and say
this is my חטאת chatat and at the end of the day
you had set aside a hundred dollars but you were able to
find a nice animal for ninety, so it wasn't clear at the
outset that only you were only going to use ninety dollars. So
the whole hundred was sanctified. You don't know what the price was
going to be and in that case what do you do with
the remaining ten dollars that was sanctified for חטאת? chatat? So the
הלכה Halacha is מותר חטאת לנדבה. motar chatat le'nedava. Money left over
for a חטאת chatat gets used for a נדבה nedava which again
means this עולה olah, sacrifice brought in the בית המקדש when
the... when the מזבח mizbeach is... No. Why? Because it was for
this particular חטאת. chatat. So you can't switch from like this חובה
chova to another חטאת.
chatat. No, no, meaning like if you could buy a חטאת chatat
for ninety dollars and buy an even nicer animal for a hundred
dollars.
Nobody's... well okay, you didn't... nobody's selling
those. All right. שאביא מהן חטאתי she'avi me'hen chatati and they also
agree that if you say "from these", that's an obvious case, שוין
שהמותר חולין shavin she'hamotar chullin the leftovers are חולין. chullin. So the
interesting מחלוקת machlokes is by the שקל Shekel but everybody agrees by
the חטאת chatat because it doesn't have a fixed price that if
you said this is חטאת, chatat, it's all sanctified. Now, אמר רבי
שמעון, amar Rabbi Shimon, so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon explains this difference.
מה בין שקלים לחטאת? ma bein shekalim le'chatat? Why is it that
there's a debate by the שקל Shekel, but there's not a debate
by the חטאת? chatat? אלא ששקלים יש להם קצבה. ela she'shekalim yesh
lahem kitzva. שקל Shekel. has a fixed limit, so anything extra בית
שמאי... Beit Shammai... בית הלל Beit Hillel could say is a טעות.
ta'ut. לחטאת אין לה קצבה. le'chatat ein la kitzva. חטאת chatat doesn't
have a fixed amount, so there's nothing that's a טעות ta'ut or
it all gets sanctified. רבי יהודה אומר. Rabbi Yehuda omer. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda doesn't necessarily buy this answer. אף שקלים אין להם קצבה.
af shekalim ein lahem kitzva. There's no necessarily absolute fixed amount for
a שקל. Shekel Why? שכשעלו ישראל מן הגולה she'ke'she'alu Yisrael min ha'gola
when they came back from the exile in the time of the
בית שני, Bayis Sheni, היו שוקלים דרכונות. hayu shoklim darkonot. They would
give דרכונות. darkonot. We had those coins before. Apparently those coins are
a שקל Shekel, and a half, three half שקלים. Shkalim And the
assumption is we'll see why the גמרא learns this from a פסוק
pasuk how it learns that. It's not so clear from the פסוק.
pasuk. But the assumption is, you know, they had to rebuild the
whole בית המקדש. They needed to do, collect more funds. So actually
they said, "This year the half שקל Shekel, will be a שקל
Shekel. and a half." Okay? And they were collecting it not just
for the קרבנות korbanot which is the normal use of the half
שקל, Shekel, but basically for building the בית המקדש. חזרו לשקול סלעים.
chazru lishkol sela'im. Then they... you know, once they started getting the
building built, they didn't need as many funds, so they went back
to collect a סלע sela which is a full שקל, Shekel not
a half שקל. Shekel, חזרו chazru and then it finally went back
to the half שקל, Shekel לשקול טבעים. lishkol teva'im. א טבעא a
tiv'a is a half שקל. Shekel, Okay. Now, ביקשו לשקול דינרים. bikshu
lishkol dinarim. They wanted to go even lower to a דינר. dinar.
א דינר a dinar is a quarter of a שקל. Shekel שני
דינרי sheni dinarei is a half שקל. Shekel. Okay, that was the
point I mentioned to you before that the... that the Roman tax
on the Jews, Fiscus Judaicus, was two דינרי, dinarei, which is a
half שקל. Shekel, Okay, so that's quite interesting. That was the Roman
tax on the Jews from the time of the... of the revolt.
Anyway, so they wanted to give a quarter of a שקל, Shekel
ולא קיבלו מהן, ve'lo kiblu me'hen, that they weren't allowed. You could
go higher than a half שקל, Shekel, but you can't go lower.
So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said, "Look, there's not a fixed amount.
You know, who says a half שקל Shekel, is fixed? There's times
they gave a full שקל, Shekel, times they gave a שקל Shekel
and a half." So אמר רבי שמעון, amar Rabbi Shimon, so רבי
שמעון said back to him, אף על פי כן יד כולן שוה.
af al pi chen yad kullan shava. Look, there are times that
they changed the amount, but whatever the amount is, everybody is giving
the same amount. Okay? So... so it could be at different times
in history different amounts are given, but at any particular time there
is a fixed amount. And you can't give more than your friend
is giving for the שקל. Shekel אבל
חטאת, aval chatat, by a חטאת, chatat, there's variation from one person
to the next, not just from one time to the
next. זה מביא בסלע וזה מביא בשתים וזה מביא בשלוש. ze mevi
be'sela ve'ze mevi be'shtayim ve'ze mevi be'shalosh. So at any given time
everybody knows what there... there is a fixed amount to the שקל
Shekel that's being given and therefore the extra can be seen as
a טעות. ta'ut. Where by a חטאת chatat there's never a fixed
amount between you and your friend, everybody could give different, and therefore
there's no concept of טעות.
ta'ut. Why shouldn't it be מותר? motar? Just bring them one for
three.
If you can find that, nobody in your village is selling animals.
You... you put aside a hundred and fifty dollars, the nicest animal
in your village is going for a hundred dollars. What are you
supposed to do? Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. And
besides that amount also
the amount that has to be paid as a
fee.
Yes, הקלבון. ha'kalbon. Oh, that's good... that's a good question. Can you
draw from the funds you put aside for הקלבון? ha'kalbon? That's a
good
question. That's a good question, presumably not. The only possibility would be
according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that said that הקלבון... ha'kalbon... is
there to round out the שקל, Shekel and he would say that
the קולבון Kalbon went towards a נדבה Nedava funds, but that's not
exactly the same as שקל Shekel funds. So, oh no, רבי מאיר
אומר לשקלים, Rabbi Meir omer l'shkalim, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said it
went exactly to the purpose of the שקל Shekel funds. So according
to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you could draw on this for the
שקל, Shekel. because he said that they were there to round out
the שקל.
shekel, And you had to put aside, bring aside both, including the
fee you put aside?
For רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, yes, but for anybody other than רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir the קולבון Kalbon was used for a different purpose
and had to come from different funds. It could not come from,
from שקל shekel funds. Yes.
And interesting this משנה Mishna has different countries where...
You mean the דרכון Darkon and the דינר? Dinar? Yeah, well they're
also talking, right, איטלקית Italkit also, yeah, איטלקי, Italki,
right,
right, right, right.
Okay, so let's take a look. המכנס פטרוט. Hamachaneis prutot. רבי יוסי
בשם רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Yosei b'shem Rabbi Elazar, מה פליגינן, Mah palginan,
what's the scenario that like הכא במאי עסקינן, Hacha b'mai askinan, what's
the scenario we're talking about, we're debating? במכנס פטרוט, Bimchaneis prutot,
when you're collecting pennies. אבל באומר אלו שקלי, Aval b'omer eilu shkalai,
you stick your hand into your coin jar and you grab out
a fistful of coins; you're not doing penny by penny. And you
say, "All of these will be for my שקל," shekel. and it
happens to be you drew out not a half שקל, shekel but
let's say a whole שקל. shekel In that case, כולי עלמא מודי
שהמותר נדבה, Kuli alma modei she-hamotar nedava,
that it wasn't penny by penny. You grabbed a fistful of coins
and you said all this is a שקל, shekel. everybody would agree
that that's not a טעות. Ta'ut. You meant everything in your hand.
If you were to bother to count, you would have realized that
there was more than a half שקל shekel. in your hand. So
there's no real error there and therefore you sanctified everything; even בית
הלל Beis Hillel would agree. רבי חייא רבי בא בשם רבי אלעזר,
Rabbi Chiya, Rabbi Ba b'shem Rabbi Elazar, they say the
opposite. No. מה פליגינן Mah palginan or פליגי... Paligi... במכנס פטרוט. Bimchaneis
prutot. We're talking about, you know, in a case again where it's
pennies, that's when there is the debate of בית הלל, Beis Hillel,
בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. אבל באומר אלו שקלי, Aval b'omer eilu shkalai,
if you take a fistful of money and you say, "This is
for my שקל," shekel כולי עלמא מודי שהמותר חולין. Kuli alma modei
she-hamotar chulin.
The opposite of what you said. In that case, everybody would agree
that you realized that you meant only from what's here is going
to be usable for my שקל shekel. and that not the excess.
It's not exactly clear why בית שמאי Beis Shammai would exactly agree
there, since בית שמאי Beis Shammai anyway generally says אין הקדש בטעות,
Ein hekdesh b'ta'ut, you know, that... that הקדש בטעות Hekdesh b'ta'ut is
הקדש. But one of the מפרשים Meforshim says again, the same point:
it's not a טעות, Ta'ut, right? You actually, if you were to
bother to check, you'd know that there was extra. So one says,
"Oh, so
since it's, you know, since clearly there's extra here, you meant to
sanctify it," and the opposite argument, "No, clearly there's extra, clearly you
didn't mean to sanctify it when you said 'This is for my
שקל,' shekel you meant a שקל's shekel worth is for my שקל."
shekel Okay, but either way, they say that when you grab a
fistful, it's different. The question is which way it goes. Okay, אמר
רבי חייא מתניתא מסייעא לרב ביבי. Amar Rabbi Chiya matnisa mesayeia l'Rav
Bibi. Our משנה Mishna supports רב ביבי Rav Bibi who says that
when you grab all the money, the rest is חולין. Chulin. How
does it support it? דתנן, Detnan, אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon,
מה בין שקלים לחטאת, Mah bein shkalim l'chatas, אלא שהשקלים יש להם
קצבה ולחטאת אין להם קצבה. Ella she-hashkalim yesh lahem kitzva ul'chatas ein
lahem kitzva.
So he makes this distinction why שקלים Shkalim, is different than the
חטאת. Chatas. The חטאת, Chatas, it always gets sanctified, not by the
extra of the שקלים. shekalim. מן אנן קיימין, Man anan kayamin, now
what's the case? היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case of, that
he says that the שקלים shekels has a different הלכה than the
חטאת? Chatas? אי באומר שאביא מהן שקלי, I b'omer she-avi mehen shkalai,
if it's the case that you said, "I'll draw on these funds
for my שקל," shekel so it's the exact same שקל shekel and
a חטאת. Chatas. כולי עלמא מודי שהמותר חולין. Kuli alma modei she-hamotar
chulin.
Everybody agrees that what's left over is חולין,
Chulin, whether you're dealing with a שקל, shekel whether... I'm sorry, that's...
כולי עלמא, Kuli alma, excuse me, בית הלל, Beis Hillel, בית שמאי
Beis Shammai agree that what's left over is חולין. Chulin. And similarly
in parallel, אי באומר שאביא מהן חטאתי, I b'omer she-avi mehen chatasi,
if you said that by חטאת, Chatas, כולי עלמא מודי שהמותר חולין.
Kuli alma modei she-hamotar chulin. Everybody would also agree. So when he
is distinguishing between חטאת Chatas and שקל, shekel it's not when you
say, "I will draw on these funds," because then obviously everybody agrees
what's left over is חולין. Chulin. אלא כינן אנן קיימין, Ella kinan
anan kayamin, what are we talking about? באומר אלו שקלי, B'omer eilu
shkalai, when you say, like the case like the גמרא is assuming,
is the case that we had just discussed, when you have that
fistful of coins and you say "These are my שקל," shekel אלו
שקלי. Eilu shkalai.
שקלים, shekalim. על ידי שקצבתן מן התורה, Al yedei she-kotzvasan min ha-Torah,
by the case of שקל shekel since there's a fixed
amount, מותר חולין, Motar chulin, what's left over is חולין. Chulin. חטאת,
Chatas, על ידי שאין קצבתן מן התורה, Al yedei she-ein kotzvasan min
ha-Torah, מותר נדבה, Motar nedava, but by a חטאת Chatas where there's
no fixed amount, so then any leftover funds go for קרבנות. Korbanos.
So that proves like רב ביבי. Rav Bibi. Now very strange because
we assume, when we read the משנה, Mishna when he said "What's
the difference between a שקל shekel. and a חטאת," Chatas, he was
saying, "Why is there a debate by the שקל shekel, and there's
no debate by the
חטאת," Chatas, right? And therefore we're talking about the case that you're
collecting pennies. Why is there a debate by שקל shekel, not a
חטאת? Chatas? The difference of a fixed amount. The גמרא assumes, when
he said, "What's the difference between שקל shekel. and חטאת," Chatas, that
he was assuming that by the שקל shekel case where both בית
הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai would agree what's left
over is חולין, Chulin, right? Not why do they debate by שקל.
shekel. Why he's assuming that everybody would agree they're both חולין chullin,
*chullin*. What would be that scenario that everybody would agree? Ah, it
must be the case we're describing with the fistful of coins. So
you see a proof that when there's a fistful of coins and
there's leftover even בית שמאי *Bais Shammai* agrees. It's not a very
big proof, the answer is obvious. So that's the גמרא *Gemara* says:
מה עביד ליה רבי יוסי בשם רבי אליעזר *Ma avid lei Rabbi
Yosi bisheim Rabbi Eliezer*? What does רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* in the
name of רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* say? He says in the case
when you have a fistful of coins, the leftover is הקדש *hekdesh*.
פשט לה במכניס פרוטות כבית הלל *Pashit lah bimachnis prutos k'Vais Hillel*.
Yeah, רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* wasn't saying that everybody agrees, he was
saying why does בית הלל Beit Hillel *Bais Hillel* say by the
שקל shekel. *shekel* the leftover is חולין chullin? *chullin* and by the
חטאת chatas *chattas* not? And here's the difference: but it's the case
of collecting pennies, if you grabbed a fistful, yeah, then the leftover
everybody would agree would be הקדש *hekdesh*. Okay? So you have this
issue, רבי שמעון's *Rabbi Shimon's* distinction in the משנה *Mishnah* between a
שקל shekel *shekel* and a חטאת *chattas* is not necessarily saying that
בית שמאי *Bais Shammai* would agree in the שקל shekel *shekel* case,
but why did בית הלל *Bais Hillel* lenient by the שקל shekel
*shekel* case? And the answer is the difference between a fixed amount
and a not fixed amount. So the גמרא *Gemara* says והתנינן *Ve-ha
t'ninan*, one minute, we have a following משנה *Mishnah* that we're going
to see in a minute that says מותר שקלים חולין *mosar shekalim
chullin*. Again, what's leftover by a שקל shekel, *shekel* is חולין *chullin*,
and again the גמרא *Gemara* is assuming that that's agreed to by
בית שמאי *Bais Shammai* and בית הלל *Bais Hillel*. So where would
be a case that בית שמאי *Bais Shammai* would agree what's leftover
is חולין *chullin*? Again, isn't it the proof that when you say
אלו elu, *eilu* and you have a fistful of it, that בית
שמאי *Bais Shammai* agrees that it's חולין *chullin*? No. Again, פשט לה
במכניס פרוטות כבית הלל *Pashit lah bimachnis prutos k'Vais Hillel*. You know,
again, not such a big question. Again, it's the case of the
standard case of pennies, and it's goes like בית הלל *Bais Hillel*.
So yes, there's evidence in the משניות Mishnayos *Mishnayos* that leftover money
from a שקל shekel *shekel* is חולין *chullin*, but that doesn't mean
that that's the case when you grab the fistful and you said
אלו elu *eilu* and בית שמאי *Bais Shammai* agrees. It could be
the standard scenario of collecting pennies and that it's according to the
position of בית הלל *Bais Hillel*. It's not a big חידוש *chiddush*
that the משנה *Mishnah* assumes we're going
like
בית הלל *Bais Hillel*. Okay, now the
גמרא *Gemara* says like this: המפריש שקלו וסבר שהוא חייב ונמצא שאינו
חייב *Hamaphrish shekalo v'savar shehu chayav v'nimtza she-eino chayav*. You set aside
your coin and you say "this is my שקל shekel *shekel*" and
you thought you obviously were obligated, turns out you weren't obligated. Why
not? I don't know. Your wife gave for
you, somebody already gave your שקל shekel *shekel* for you, turned out
when you gave you totally forgotten you know that you gave yourself
three months ago. And now what's the status of this? That would
seem like a הקדש טעות ta'us. *hekdesh ta'us* case, you sanctified it,
you didn't realize. So לא קדש *lo kadash*, לא קידש *lo kideish*,
you didn't sanctify, presumably that's אליבא דבית הלל *aliba d'Bais Hillel*. It
could be בית שמאי *Bais Shammai* would disagree. Now, המפריש שנים וסבר
שהוא חייב שנים ונמצא שאינו חייב אלא אחד *Hamaphrish shenayim v'savar shehu
chayav shenayim v'nimtza she-eino chayav ela echad*, you put aside two, you
thought that you hadn't paid last year's שקל shekel *shekel* and you
put aside two, one for this year one for last year, and
you say "these two are for my שקל shekel *shekel*" and it
turns out that you did pay last year's שקל shekel *shekel* and
you only חייב *chayav* one. So it would seem it's the same
issue, one is a טעות ta'us. *ta'us* and it shouldn't be קדוש
kadosh *kadosh*. In this case, השני מה עביד ליה *hashaini mah avid
lei*? What would be the status of the second one? נשמנה מן
הדא min hada. *Nishmanah min hada*, let's hear it from there. הפריש
חטאתו וסבר שהוא חייב ונמצא שאינו חייב *Hifrish chattaso v'savar shehu chayav
v'nimtza she-eino chayav*. If you separated a חטאת *chattas* and you thought
you were obligated a חטאת *chattas* and you weren't, לא קידשה *lo
kidsha*, you didn't sanctify it because that's again בית הלל *Bais Hillel*
that הקדש בטעות *hekdesh b'ta'us* is not הקדש *hekdesh*. הפריש שנים וסבר
שהוא חייב שנים *Hifrish shenayim v'savar shehu chayav shenayim*, you set aside
two חטאות *chattasos* you sanctified them and you thought you were חייב
*chayav* two, ונמצא שאינו חייב אלא אחד *v'nimtza she-eino chayav ela echad*,
and it turned out you were less of a sinner than you
thought and you're only חייב *chayav* one, אותה השניה מה את עביד
לה *osah hashniyah mah at avid lah*? What's the הלכה *halacha* with
the second one? אלא רועה *Ela ro-eh*, it must be that it
would graze. הכא נמי hacha nami. *Hacha nami*, so here too. Meaning
nobody would think in the חטאת *chattas* case that it would not
be sanctified. Now why is not clear, isn't it the exact same
question? You know somehow the way we have the language of the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* is quite interesting. It's say let me try to
prove your case and it doesn't bring a textual proof, it actually
just brings like
a סברא *svara* scenario, you know not just from a not just
from like a text. So some switch the גירסא *girsa* and they
take out the lines מה את עביד לה *mah at avid lah*
and basically say that it's quoting a text and the text says
explicitly השני רועה *hashani ro-eh*. So that you know it's not a
סברא *svara* point it's like look we have a text that says
by a חטאת *chattas* the second one would graze. Now what is
the logic of the difference? So the מפרשים meforshim *mefarshim* just say
that in that case since the הקדש *hekdesh* is taking effect on
one, maybe it's a case that בית הלל *Bais Hillel* would agree.
Meaning if I give a penny and I say you know "this
is הקדש *hekdesh*" and I don't you know "this is a שקל
shekel. *shekel*" and I don't realize that I already have my half
שקל shekel. *shekel* in there, that's a טעות ta'us, *ta'us*. But if
I'm sanctifying two animals or two חצי שקלים *chatzi shekalim*, not just
one, and the קדושה *kedusha* works for one and the other is
a mistake, maybe since it's taking effect for one even though I'm
making a mistake it takes effect for both. That seems to be
the argument. Now okay so that would be the הלכה *halacha* here
if you did two שקלים *shekalim* and you were really only חייב
*chayav* one. Now but if that's the... True, says the גמרא, one
minute, we have a case when you're doing a lot of things
at once and there's a partial טעות. That's the case of the
fistful of coins, right? Isn't that exactly the case of the fistful
of coins where you say this is my שקל, shekel that it
works for some of that money, and the question is what's the
status for the rest of the money? So that's exactly now what
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi, says. If that's the case says the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi
הכא נמי. So here too, אלו לנדבה. elu linedavah. So היכא את
אמר אלו? heicha at omar elu? So here where it would be
this would sort of prove to you that when you said אלו,
elu. when you said these and you had a whole fistful of
them, that that the leftover would not be חולין, the leftover would
be לנדבה, linedavah, would be הקדש, because once it takes effect for
one it takes effect for the rest even though there's a
טעות. אלו elu means אלו. elu, So היכא את אמרת אלו? heicha
at omarta elu? So how could you say before that if in
the case of אלו the leftover money would be חולין? Okay so
this ties back to that earlier debate, would בית הלל agree when
you grab the fistful and you said אלו, would they agree that
the leftover there would be קדוש even though there's a טעות, maybe
it's different once the הקדש took effect on part of it. And
that's like the case of setting aside two שקלים. Okay, let's continue
now. רבי יהודה אומר. Rabbi Yehuda omer. Now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
makes this point about how there would be periods in history where
they would go higher than a half שקל shekel, but never low.
So דרכונות darkonot are דינרין. dinrin. What are דרכונות, darkonot, they're דינרין.
dinrin. Now they're not really and I didn't have a chance to
check the גרסאות, girsa'ot, but a דינרא dinara is actually a quarter
of a שקל. shekel But maybe it's some דינר dinar that was
that was in the time of the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that actually was
a שקל shekel and a half. We're going to find out that
a דרכון darkon is a שקל shekel and a half. I don't
know if they quote anywhere any alternative texts or anything. Anyway, okay,
that's דרכון. darkon. Now חזו
לשקול סלעים, chazu lishkot sla'im, what are סלעים? sla'im? כשמן. kishmo'an. Like
a סלע. sela. You know what a סלע sela is, okay, so
it's a סלע. sela. חזו לשקול טיבין, chazu lishkot tivin, then they
went down from a סלע's sela a full שקל. shekel. They went
down to a טיבין, tivin, פלגי סלעים, palgi sla'im, that's a half
סלע. sela. ביקשו לשקול דינרין, bikshu lishkot dinarin, then they wanted to
go to דינרין, dinarin, קרטין. kartin. Those are what we would nowadays
call a קרטין. kartin. דרכונות darkonot nowadays we call דינרין. dinrin. דינרין
dinrin is what we would call קרטין. kartin. Anyway, קרטין kartin is
a quarter שקל. shekel ולא קיבלו עליהם, v'lo kibelu aleihem, and they
refused to accept that. מן הדא. min hada. Okay, so ולא קיבלו
עליהם, v'lo kibelu aleihem, that they wouldn't do it. That's the word
karat?
Maybe. Okay, yeah.
So doesn't
it make sense the people changed?
Yeah, it's interesting. Maybe? Well, it's actually quite different. The משנה says
ולא קיבלו מהן. v'lo kibelu meihen. They wouldn't accept from them, which
means the authorities wouldn't accept that that was sufficient. This says ולא
קיבלו עליהם, v'lo kibelu aleihem, which means the people refused to accept
that. So it's interesting who's refusing.
I would assume the people would rather give less.
Right? Okay,
so anyway מן הדא. Now, where do you get the idea that
they initially gave a שקל shekel and a half, this דרכון, darkon,
from the following פסוק? pasuk? והעמדנו עלינו מצוות לתת שלישית השקל בשנה
לעבודת בית אלוהינו. V'ha'amadnu aleinu mitzvat lateit shlishit hashekel bashanah la'avodat beit
eloheinu. So this is when they started to rebuild the בית המקדש,
we have to give in a year a third of a שקל.
shekel So how does a third of a שקל shekel. get you
to a שקל shekel, and a half? So first of all I
should point out that this פסוק pasuk is the basis in the
בבלי, Bavli, where the בבלי Bavli says that even if somebody gives
like no צדקה, tzedakah, minimally you should give you need to give
a third of a שקל shekel. a year based on this פסוק,
pasuk, like that's a minimum צדקה. tzedakah. That's an interesting transfer from
the idea of שקל shekel. to the בית המקדש to צדקה tzedakah
requirements, which we're going to actually get to in a minute in
a somewhat of a similar parallel. Here, how does the third of
a שקל shekel, get you to a שקל shekel. and a half?
So could be the ירושלמי is just reading it as a third,
reading it as not as a third, but as three. And three
half שקלים is a שקל shekel. and a half. How do you
read a third as three? I don't know. Because it could have
said שליש shlish and it says שלישית. shlishit. Others say that the
שקל shekel. at the time
of the beginning of the second
בית המקדש was what would it be? I guess it would be
four and a half שקלים. So a third of it was a
שקל shekel. and a half. Basically it was a more expensive coin.
So anyway, exactly how we get it is not so clear. Yes,
Charlie?
Yes, Shishtos quotes רמב"ם Rambam as saying a דרכון darkon is a
half שקל. shekel A what? A דרכון, darkon, a דרכון.
darkon. He says that רמב"ם Rambam and
others disagree with him.
Alright, so I don't know what to do with that. Okay, so
let's take a look now as the yeah, I'll just read you
the one line.
Oh,
one minute. No, no, no, oh, no, no, okay no I misstated
it. Here's what here's the interpretation. It says that it says a
third of a שקל, shekel ah here's the interpretation, it says a
third of a שקל, shekel. but the assumption is they would never
give less than what the תורה Torah says, which is a half
of a שקל. shekel So we have to assume that that third
of a שקל at that time was actually equivalent to a biblical
half שקל. Fine, that only gets you to a half שקל. How
do you know it gets you to a שקל and a half?
So that's the next line of the גמרא that we're going to
say that they actually collected this not once but three times. So
let's take a look. So it says, וחילקין בשם רב אחא מכאן
שצריך אדם לשלש שקליו ג' פעמים בשנה. V'chilkin b'shem Rav Acha, mikan
shetzarich adam l'shalesh shekalav gimel p'amim bashanah.
Here you see you have to give your שקל three times in
a year. Now, does that mean what does that mean like not
בזמן הזה, bazman hazeh, I mean so what does it mean מכאן,
mikan, but the assumption being anyway that then they made that third
of a שקל donation somehow we're learning out that they made the
third of a שקל, they made it three times and that that
שקל was worth a שקל and a half. So somehow we get
from this the idea that they initially gave a שקל and a
half.
Multiplied over a year or...
No,
so it says the full amount of the third שקל which the
claim is is equal to a half שקל was three times, so
three times a half is one and a half, so that the
initial giving was one and a half. But anyway, but we're also
transferring it into an argument about how you give your general donation
to to צדקה tzedakah or to to a שול shul or whatnot
and it seems like part of the point is like split your
donations over multiple times of year. It's like the רמב"ם Rambam says
by the משנה in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avos, the
one of the cryptic משניות in פרקי אבות Pirkei Avos says, הכל
לפי
רוב המעשה ולא לפי
גודל
המעשה, Hakol lefi rov hamaaseh velo lefi godel hamaaseh, something like that.
לפי המעשה ולא לפי גודל המעשה. Lefi hamaaseh velo lefi godel hamaaseh.
Anyway, the way the רמב"ם Rambam explains it is he says it
means that it's better to give a thousand times a dollar to
צדקה tzedakah than write one one thousand dollar check to צדקה tzedakah
because it inculcates much more the trait of giving and of charity
and of generosity and so on. So anyway, that's a way to
read this as well, you know, spread out your donations over the
times. So then the גמרא also says, מכאן שאין מטריחין על הציבור
יותר מג' פנים בשנה. mikan she'ein matrichin al hatzibur yoser migimel panim
bashanah.
Here's another way of looking at it: don't make more than three
appeals during the year. Okay. How many שולס shuls pay attention to
that one I'd like to know? Alright. אמר רבי אבין Amar Rebbe
Abin מכאן לג' mikan ligimel now this idea of three again in
the in the פסוק pasuk of the third but there's a whole
three theme going on by the שקל anyway. ג' סאין מכאן לג'
קופות, Gimel se'in mikan ligimel kuppos, we're going to see in a
later משנה that the baskets they used to collect from the שופרות
shofrot. they used three baskets to collect. Each basket would hold ג'
סאין. gimel se'in. Okay. מכאן לג' הפרשות mikan ligimel hafrashos and they
would take and they would
take and they would take three three times they would remove the
money from the שופרות. So basically we're going to see in a
later משנה that there's a whole major theme of three going around
by the שקל. So it says it comes from this פסוק. pasuk.
So on this פסוק pasuk we learn now again, okay, so so
this פסוק pasuk we learn whole themes of three by שקל. We
learn also that they would give somehow we learn they would give
a שקל and a half and maybe we also learn something in
terms of practically spreading out your צדקה tzedakah or about the שול
shul not making demands too many times during the year and so
on. Let's finish this up. כתיב Kasiv זה
יתנו כל העובר על הפקודים. Zeh yitnu kol haover al hapikudim. This
is what you should give whoever gets counted. רבי יהודה ורבי נחמיה.
Rebbe Yehuda ve'Rebbe Nechemia. חד אמר Chad amar now we're a little
דרשה. drasha. Why is it, since we're talking about the amount, why
is it that they gave a מחצית השקל? machatzis hashekel? What's the
symbolic significance of the מחצית השקל? machatzis hashekel? So חד אמר לפי
שחטאו במחצית היום יתנו במחצית השקל. chad amar lefi shechatu bmachatzis hayom
yitnu bmachatzis hashekel. The חטא cheit was in the middle of the
day, right, cause the
פסוק pasuk is כי בשש משה. ki boshesh Moshe. משה Moshe hesitated
and the דרשה drasha is בא שש. ba shesh. There were six
hours into the day. No, they all agree to that. I understand,
but anyway the חטא cheit was at noon according to חז"ל Chazal
and therefore you give a half of a שקל, half day. Now
of course chronologically in the תורה Torah the מצוה mitzvah of giving
the מחצית השקל machatzis hashekel in כי תשא Ki Tisa comes before
the חטא העגל, cheit ha'egel, okay, but if רש"י Rashi sort of
understands that it's out of order and the חטא העגל cheit ha'egel
happens first. All of these דרשות drashos here assume that the מחצית
השקל, machatzis hashekel, maybe you could say God commanded it knowing there
would be a חטא העגל cheit ha'egel that raises other questions. Anyway,
it all understands that even though in the תורה Torah it appears
before חטא העגל, cheit ha'egel, it was seen as a תיקון tikkun
for the חטא העגל. cheit ha'egel. Just one second, let's just finish
at the end
here. So חד אמר לפי שחטאו בשש שעות ביום יתנו מחצית השקל
דהוי שיתא גרמיסין. chad amar lefi shechatu b'shesh sha'os bayom yitnu machatzis
hashekel d'avei sheisha garmisin. Cause a half of a שקל is worth
six גרמיסין garmisin which was some other type of a coin. So
it's the same idea except rather than emphasizing half, it emphasizes six.
Some of the מפרשים say the difference of this is is that
as we've seen you can go higher in what you give for
the מחצית השקל, machatzis hashekel, so according to the first approach you
would always try to do a half of some coin, even if
you're going to change the amount to go up, you would want
the symbolism of a half. And according to the other approach, you
want the symbolism of six, so even if you change the money
and go up, you want it to be six of some type
of a smaller coin. Joe, what were you going to say?
That's a very tenuous connection but it would be much more related
to the עגל egel than you have to give gold.
Right,
right, exactly, exactly, yes.
Why should they frame this in terms of payment for sin rather
than
everybody's special to everyone else, it's all our responsibility?
Right. It's a very good point, you know. Now it was also
for the, there was a שקל that was for the sockets, which
was for the building of the בית המקדש, which, you know, was
also true in the בית שני Bayis Sheni presumably that's why they
were collecting more, but the general שקל was for the קרבנות korbanos
and, you know, and the קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur. קרבן ציבור korban
tzibur could be seen as much more sin-related, although it is true
that the daily קרבן ציבור korban tzibur was an עולה, olah. and
the מוסף musaf was primarily an עולה. חטאת was a small piece
of that. But you are right, why it's sort of underscoring the
sin part of it and the עגל egel is, you know, is
a very good question. Let's finish with the symbolisms and get to
the end. Okay. רבי יהושע בי רבי נחמיה בשם רבי יוחנן בן
זכאי Rabbi Yehoshua bei Rabbi Nechemia beshem Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai לפי
שעברו על עשרת הדברות lefi she'avru al Aseret HaDibrot יתן כל אחד
ואחד עשרה גרה. yitein kol echad ve'echad asara geira. Right away, half
a שקל. A שקל was עשרים גרה. esrim geira. So he says
this would be עשרה גרה. asara geira. עשרה גרה asara geira for
the עשרת הדברות. Aseret HaDibrot. So you thought they were just over
on עבודה זרה? avoda zara? No. I mean, the whole לוחות luchos
were broken. So you have to repair that. רבי ברכיה, רבי לוי
בשם רבי שמעון לקיש Rabbi Berachia, Rabbi Levi beshem Rabbi Shimon Lakish
לפי שמכרו בכורה של רחל בעשרים כסף. lefi shemachru bechora shel Rachel
beesrim kesef. This is sort of like what we read in אלה
אזכרה. Eleh Ezkerah. Like, oh my god, we're still paying back for
the sin of selling of selling יוסף. Yosef. So it says they
sold יוסף Yosef for עשרים כסף. esrim kesef. Okay, now עשרים כסף,
esrim kesef, a שקל is, is, is עשרה גרה הכסף. asara geira
hakesef. Right. No, no, no, no, I know that. But a שקל
is four, what do you call it, four זוז, zuz, four זוז?
zuz? I'm sorry. No, four דינר. dinar. Four דינרים. dinarim. Right, right.
'Cause a דינר dinar is a quarter of a שקל.
Four דינר. dinar. So it assumes that the עשרים כסף esrim kesef
is עשרים דינר. esrim dinar. Okay? So if it's עשרים דינר, esrim
dinar, and four דינר dinar to a שקל, so that's five שקל.
Okay, you all with me? עשרים כסף esrim kesef is if it's
four דינר, dinar, then it's five שקל. So לפי שמכרו בכורה של
רחל בעשרים כסף lefi shemachru bechora shel Rachel beesrim kesef יהי כל
אחד ואחד פודה את בנו בכורו בעשרים כסף. yehei kol echad ve'echad
podeh es beno bechoro beesrim kesef. So we're skipping, we're no longer
on the מחצית השקל. machatzis hashekel. What's the פדיון הבכור? pidyon habechor?
Five שקל, right? And what, so עשרים כסף esrim kesef of יוסף,
Yosef, if it's, if it's עשרים דינר, esrim dinar, it's five שקל.
They sold יעקב's Yaakov בכור, bechor, well not יעקב, Yaakov, רחל's Rachel
בכור bechor for five שקל. So we do פדיון בכור pidyon bechor
for five שקל. Okay. רב פנחס בשם רב לוי Rav Pinchas beshem
Rav Levi לפי שמכרו בכורה של רחל בעשרים כסף lefi shemachru bechora
shel Rachel beesrim kesef ונפל כל אחד ואחד מהם טיבע. venafal kol
echad ve'echad meihem teiva. How much did every brother get? How many
brothers were in on the deal? Ten, not בנימין. Binyamin. So if
you get עשרים כסף, esrim kesef, that's two כסף kesef per brother.
A כסף kesef is a דינר. dinar. Two דינר dinar per brother.
We said two דינר dinar is a half שקל. Okay, a דינר
dinar is what the גמרא calls בכור טיבעין.
bechor teiva'in. Now how do you get ten?
ראובן wasn't in on it. All right, but in the end he
took part, he divided the money with him as well. So anyway,
everybody got, you missed that part of the story, okay? Anyway, so
everybody got a half שקל out of the deal. If they got
five שקל for it, they divide by ten, everybody got a half
שקל. אה, וזקוק כל אחד ואחד נותן שקלו. ah, vezakuk kol echad
ve'echad nosein shiklo. Therefore we all give our half שקל and to
be, to be מכפר mechaper for this original sin.
Yeah, but then people from שבט יוסף Shevet Yosef shouldn't
have to give according to you.
All right. Yes. Regarding how often you collect צדקה, tzedakah, the קופה
was collected and distributed every week.
Right, right. No, that's true. So what it means be מטיל על
הציבור? matil al hatzibur? Yeah, it'd be interesting to know. Maybe it
meant for temple, for, for, for שול, shul, for support for שול.
shul. I don't know exactly how they assume that would transition. But
you're right, obviously there were daily donations to the poor, but maybe
this is not צדקה tzedakah related as much as
it is sort of,
you know, מקדש mikdash related or contemporary. Okay, so we'll
end here. I don't know what we're going to do. We're already
a full half דף behind, but we will stop here.